Guide to the Marcelo DeMoura Papers 1941-1999 MSS.112
Fales Library and Special Collections
Marcelo DeMoura Papers
1941-1999
1982-1999
Fales Library and Special Collections
DeMoura, Marcelo
MSS.112
2.76 Linear Feet In 1 record carton, 1 document case, 1 oversize box.
Marcelo DeMoura is an animation artist and collector of animation artworks. The Marcelo DeMoura Papers contain original drawings and animation cels, as well as copies of additional drawings and Disney movie drafts.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Marcelo DeMoura Papers were acquired from Marcelo DeMoura by the Fales Library in 2001. The accession number associated with this gift is 2001.112
Arrangement
Series I: Original Works (Oversize)
Series II: Photocopied Drawings
Series III: Drafts and Story Boards
Oversize Series II: Photocopied Drawings
Materials are divided into three series, and arranged alphabetically by film title within each series.
Biographical Note
Marcelo DeMoura, animator and collector of animation, has worked in the animation departments of such films as Thumbelina (1994), The Iron Giant (1999), and Ice Age (2002). He has also directed animated programs in his native Brazil.
Related Materials
John Canemaker Animation Collection (MSS 040)
Scope and Content
The bulk of the Marcelo DeMoura Papers consists of original artworks and photocopied animation drawings that span a date range from 1982-1999. The collection also contains photostats of model sheets, drafts, and scripts from Disney films dating back to 1941. A large quantity of the original artworks, some of which feature the artist's signature, were drawn by noted animator and director Don Bluth.
Animation; Drawings; Alice in Wonderland (Motion picture: 1951); Aladdin (Motion picture); Animation cels; Animated films.; Animators -- United States; Sword in the stone (Motion picture); Mickey and the beanstalk (Motion picture); Xanadu (Motion picture); 101 Dalmatians (Motion picture: 1961); Dumbo (Motion picture); Make mine music (Motion picture); Cinderella (Motion picture); DeMoura, Marcelo; Bluth, Don; Walt Disney Productions
- Series I: Original Works (Oversize)
  Arrangement note
  Materials are divided by format into two Subseries (Drawings and Animation cels), and arranged alphabetically by title within each subseries.
  Scope and Content
  This series contains all of the original artworks in the archive. Subseries A features a particularly strong collection of drawings from The Secret of Nimh (1982). Strengths of Subseries B include animation cels from Thumbelina (1994). Some of the animation cels are signed by Don Bluth (see notes below item descriptions).
  - Subseries A: Drawings
    - Aladdin, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General
      Contents:
      Jasmine drawing by Glen Keane (1)
    - All Dogs Go to Heaven, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Kate markup color sheet (1)
    - An American Tail, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Fievel production drawings (2)
    - Banjo and the Woodpile Cat, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Banjo production drawings (6)
    - The Iron Giant, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Hogarth production drawings (2)
    - The King and I, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      King production drawing (1)
    - The Secret of Nimh, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
      Mrs. Brisby production drawings (8)
      Mrs. Brisby production color markups (24)
      Nicodemus production drawings (6)
      Nicodemus production color markups (13)
      Auntie Shrew production drawings (7)
      Auntie Shrew production color markups (2)
      Sullivan production color markups (4)
      Mrs. Brisby and Mr. Ages production color markups (5)
      Teresa production color markups (3)
      Owl production color markups (4)
      Cynthia production color markups (1)
      Flowers production color markups (1)
      Jenner production color markups (6)
      Jenner and Sullivan production color markups (2)
      Dragon production color markups (2)
    - Space Ace, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Borg production drawings (2)
  - Subseries B: Animation cels
    - All Dogs Go to Heaven, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12-25)
      Annemarie cel, signed by Don Bluth (2)
      Charlie cel (4)
      Itchy cel (2)
      Dog cel (1)
      Charlie and Itchy cel (1)
      Charlie, Itchy and Dog cel (4)
    - An American Tail, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Tiger cel, signed by Don Bluth (1)
    - Banjo and the Woodpile Cat, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
      Crazy Legs production cels (2), one with copy background
    - Rock-A-Doodle, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
      Owl production cel (2)
    - The Secret of Nimh, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 31-33)
      Mrs. Brisby and Nicodemus cel (2)
      Mr. Ages cel with copy of background (1)
    - Space Ace (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
      Borg as human production cel (1)
      Ace cel signed by Don Bluth (1)
    - Thumbelina, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 36-48)
      Thumbelina production cel (3)
      Ma Toad production cel (2)
      Prince Cornelius production model sheet (1)
      Thumbelina and Prince Cornelius production cel (6)
      Watercolor inspirational concept (1)
      Note: Folders 43 (Prince Cornelius production model sheet) and 44-47 (Thumbelina and Prince Cornelius production cels) are currently restricted due to preservation concerns.
    - A Troll in Central Park, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 49-50)
      Gus cel (1)
      Stanley cel, signed by Don Bluth (1)
    - Xanadu, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 51-54)
      Bird cel, signed by Don Bluth (2)
      Fish cel (2)
- Series II: Photocopied Drawings
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by title.
  Series II contains photocopies of individual scenes from various animated films. Strengths of this series include drawings from An American Tail (1986).
  - An American Tail, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Banjo and the Woodpile Cat, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Dragon's Lair, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
  - The Iron Giant, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 11-14)
  - The Pebble and the Penguin, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Peter Pan, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Rock-A-Doodle, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - The Secret of Nimh, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - The Tigger Movie, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Unidentified Drawings, undated (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
- Series III: Drafts and Story Boards
  This series contains story boards from Rocket Power (1999), a television series on which DeMoura served as story artist, as well as script drafts of a number of Disney films, including Dumbo (1941) and Alice in Wonderland (1951).
  - 101 Dalmatians draft, 1961 (release date) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Alice in Wonderland draft, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Cinderella draft, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Dumbo draft, 1941 (release date) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Ichabod Crane draft, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Make Mine Music draft, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mickey and the Beanstalk draft, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Rescuers Down Under draft, 24 Oct 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Rocket Power story boards, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Saludos Amigos draft, 1942 (release date) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Sword in the Stone draft, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - The Three Caballeros draft, 1944 (release date) (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Oversize Series II: Photocopied Drawings
  - Disney production Photostats of Model Sheets (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Contains photostats from: Pluto's Fledgling (1941), So Dear to My Heart (1946), Primitive Pluto (1947), "Lambert Wolf" (1953), and Moby Duck (1966).